I want to help you re-perceive what philanthropy is,
أريد أن أساعدكم أن تعيدو النظر في ماهية العمل الخيري ،
what it could be,
ماذا يمكن أن يكون
and what your relationship to it is.
وماهية علاقتك به
And in doing that, I want to offer you a vision,
وبعملنا هذا ، أريد أن أهديكم رؤية
an imagined future, if you will,
مستقبل مٌرام ، إذا أردتم
of how, as the poet Seamus Heaney has put it,
وكيف شرحه الشاعر سيمز هييني
"Once in a lifetime
"مرة في العمر
the longed-for tidal wave of justice can rise up,
مد موجة الرغبة بالعدالة قد يرتفع
and hope and history rhyme."
ويصنع أملاً وسجعاً تاريخي
I want to start with these word pairs here.
أريد أن أبدأ بهذا الزوج من الكلمات هنا
We all know which side of these we'd like to be on.
كلنا نعرف أي جانب من هذه نريد أن نكون
When philanthropy was reinvented a century ago,
عندما أعيد تعريف العمل الإنساني منذ عقد
when the foundation form was actually invented,
وعندما تشكلت البنية الأساسية
they didn't think of themselves on the wrong side of these either.
لم يفكروا في أنفسهم في الجانب الخطأ من هذه كذلك
In fact they would never have thought of themselves
في الحقيقة أنه لايمكن أنهم فكروا بأنفسهم
as closed and set in their ways,
كمنغلقين وثابتين بطريقتهم
as slow to respond to new challenges,
كبطء ردهم على التحديات الجديدة
as small and risk-averse.
كصغار مرغمين على المغامرة
And in fact they weren't. They were reinventing charity in those times,
وفي الحقيقة هم ليسو كذلك ، بل إعادو إختراع العمل الخيري في تلك الأيام
what Rockefeller called "the business of benevolence."
وما يسميه روكفيلر "تجارة الإهدائات"
But by the end of the 20th century,
ولكن بإنتهاء القرن العشرين
a new generation of critics and reformers
جيل جديد من النقاد والإصلاحيين
had come to see philanthropy just this way.
قد أتو ليجدوا العمل الإنساني كما هو بهذه الطريقة
The thing to watch for
الشي الذي ننظر إليه
as a global philanthropy industry comes about --
لصناعة عمل إنساني عالمي
and that's exactly what is happening --
وهذا بالضبط ماهو حاصل
is how the aspiration is to flip
كيف أن هذا الإلهام يتغير
these old assumptions,
هذه الإفتراضات القديمة
for philanthropy to become open and big
للعمل الإنساني ليكون مفتوحاً و ضخماً
and fast and connected, in service of the long term.
وسريع ومتصل ، ليخدم أهدافاً بعيده المدي
This entrepreneurial energy
طاقة المبادرة هذه
is emerging from many quarters.
لينضج من أقطاب عده
And it's driven and propelled forward by new leaders, like many of the people here,
وهو مسير ويسحبه للأمام قادة جدد ، ككثير من الناس هنا
by new tools, like the ones we've seen here,
عبر أدوات جديدة ، كالتي نراها هنا
and by new pressures.
وبضغوط جديدة
I've been following this change for quite a while now, and participating in it.
وقد تابعت هذا التغيير لفترة من الزمن ، وشاركت فيه
This report is our main public report.
هذا التقرير هو التقرير العام الرئيسي لنا
What it tells is the story of how today
وما يحكيه هو قصة كيف أن اليوم
actually could be as historic
حقيقةً يمكن أن يكون تاريخياً
as 100 years ago.
مقارنة بمائة سنة مضت
What I want to do is share some of the coolest things
وما أريد فعله هو مشاركتكم بعض الإشياء الممتعه
that are going on with you.
التي تحصل معكم
And as I do that, I'm not going to dwell much
وعندما أفعل هذا فلن أطيل عليكم
on the very large philanthropy that everybody already knows about --
بالأعمال الإجتماعية الكبرى التي كلنا نعرفها
the Gates or the Soros or the Google.
أعمال جيتس ، سوروس ، قوقل
Instead, what I want to do
بدلاً ، ما أريد أن أفعله
is talk about the philanthropy of all of us:
هو التكلم عن تطوع كل منا
the democratization of philanthropy.
ديمقراطية العمل الخيري
This is a moment in history when the average person
هذه لحظة تاريخية عندما يكون للشخص العادي
has more power than at any time.
قوة أكبر من أي وقت مضى
What I'm going to do is look at five categories of experiments,
وما سأفعله هو النظر لخمسة تصنيفات من التجارب
each of which challenges an old assumption of philanthropy.
كل منها يواجه تحديات المفاهيم القديمة للعمل الإجتماعي
The first is mass collaboration, represented here by Wikipedia.
الأول هو العمل التشاركي الجماعي ، ممثلا هنا بويكيبيديا
Now, this may surprise you.
الآن، ربما يفاجئكم هذا
But remember, philanthropy is about giving of time and talent, not just money.
ولكن تذكروا ، العمل الإجتماعي هو عطاء من الوقت والمهارة وليس المال فقط
Clay Shirky, that great chronicler of everything networked,
كلاي شيركي ، ذلك الموثق العظيم لكل شي متصل بشبكات
has captured the assumption that this challenges
قد استخلص هذه الفرضية بأن هذا التحدي
in such a beautiful way.
يكون بهذه الطريقة الجميلة
He said, "We have lived in this world
هو قال " نحن عشنا في هذا العالم
where little things are done for love
حيث بعض الأشياء الصغيرة التي نفعلها من أجل الحب
and big things for money.
والأشياء الكبرى للمال
Now we have Wikipedia.
والآن لدينا ويكيبيديا
Suddenly big things can be done for love."
فجأة قد تحصل أشياء كبيرة من أجل الحب
Watch, this spring, for Paul Hawken's new book --
ترقبوا ، هذا الربيع ، كتاب باول هاوكن الجديد
Author and entrepreneur many of you may know about.
المؤلف والمبادر لكثير من الأعمال التي تعرفونها
The book is called "Blessed Unrest."
الكتاب أسمه "الاضطرابات المباركة"
And when it comes out, a series of wiki sites
وعندما ظهر علناً ، سلسلة من مواقع المشاركة المعلوماتية ويكي
under the label WISER, are going to launch at the same time.
تحت عنوان "أكثر حكمة " ، أنها ستطلق في نفس الوقت
WISER stands for World Index
وايزر "أكثر حكمة" تأتي من الحروف الأول لـ"
for Social and Environmental Responsibility.
الفهرس العالمي للمسؤولية الإجتماعية والبيئية "
WISER sets out to document, link and empower
"أكثر حكمة" خرجت في مؤلفات لتربط و تدعم
what Paul calls the largest movement,
ما يسميه باول الحركة الأعظم
and fastest-growing movement in human history:
و الحركة الأسرع نمواً في تاريخ البشرية
humanity's collective immune response
إستجابة مناعة البشرية الجماعية
to today's threats.
لمخاطر اليوم
Now, all of these big things for love -- experiments --
الآن ، كل هذه الأعمال الكبيرة لأجل الحب
aren't going to take off.
سوف لن تقلع
But the ones that do
ولكن التي ستقلع
are going to be the biggest, the most open,
ستكون الأعظم ، والأكثر إنفتاحاً
the fastest, the most connected form of philanthropy in human history.
الأسرع ، والشكل الأكثر تواصلاً للعمل الخيري في تاريخ البشرية
Second category is online philanthropy marketplaces.
والتنصيف الثاني هو سوق العمل الإجتماعي الإلكتروني
This is, of course, to philanthropy
هذا بالطبع من أجل العمل الخيري
what eBay and Amazon are to commerce.
بينما eBay وAmazon يهدفون للربح
Think of it as peer-to-peer philanthropy.
فكروا بها كمشاركة فرد لفرد كعمل خيري
And this challenges yet another assumption,
وهذه التحديات حتى الآن إفتراض أخر
which is that organized philanthropy is only for the very wealthy.
بأن العمل الإنساني المنظم فقط للأثرياء جداً
Take a look, if you haven't, at DonorsChoose.
ألقو نظرة ، إذا لم تفلعوا ، على DonorsChoose
Omidyar Network has made a big investment in DonorsChoose.
شبكة أميقورا استثمرت كثيراً في DonorsChoose
It's one of the best known of these new marketplaces
أنه أحد أفضل الأسواق الجديدة المتعارف عليها
where a donor can go straight into a classroom
حيث يمكن للمتبرعين أن يذهبوا مباشرة لقاعة الدرس
and connect with what a teacher says they need.
ويتواصلو مع أستاذ يقول مايحتاجون إلى سماعه
Take a look at Changing the Present,
ألقو نظرة على تغيير الحاضر ،
started by a TEDster, next time you need a wedding present or a holiday present.
حيث بدأ من تيدستر "عضو تيد"، في المرة المقبلة التي تحتاج هدية زواج أو ميلاد
GiveIndia is for a whole country.
GiveIndia "جيف إنديا" لكل البلد
And it goes on and on.
وتستمر كذلك ...
The third category is represented by Warren Buffet,
التصنيف الثالث ممثل في وارن بوفت
which I call aggregated giving.
ما أسميه المنح المجمّعة
It's not just that Warren Buffet was so amazingly generous
ليس فقط أن وارن بافت شخص كريم جداً
in that historic act last summer.
بتصرفه التاريخي في الصيف الماضي
It's that he challenged another assumption,
ولكنه أيضاً تحدى إفتراض أخر
that every giver should have his or her own
أن كل متبرع يجب أن يملك
fund or foundation.
مؤسسة أو جمعيه تحمل أسمه
There are now, today, so many new funds
هناك الآن ، اليوم ، العديد من المؤسسات الخيرية
that are aggregating giving and investing,
التي تجمع التبرعات وتستثمر
bringing together people
تجمع الناس سوياً
around a common goal, to think bigger.
حول هدف موحد ، بأن يطمحوا أكبر
One of the best known is Acumen Fund, led by Jacqueline Novogratz,
" أكيومن "واحد من أفضل الصناديق المعروفة ، بقيادة جاكويلين نوفوجراتز
a TEDster who got a big boost here at TED.
عضو في تيد والذي حظي بدعم كبير هنا في تيد
But there are many others: New Profit in Cambridge,
ولكن هناك أخرين كثر. الفائدة الجديدة في كامبردج
New School's Venture Fund in Silicon Valley,
صندوق المدارس الجديدة الإستثماري في وادي السيلكون
Venture Philanthropy Partners in Washington,
شركاء الإستثمار الخيري في واشنطن
Global Fund for Women in San Francisco.
الصندوق العالمي للمرأة في سان فرانسيسكو
Take a look at these.
ألقو نظرة على هذه
These funds are to philanthropy
هذه الصناديق هي للعمل الإنساني
what venture capital, private equity, and eventually mutual funds
الصناديق الإستثمارية ، الأسهم الخاصة ، ولاحقاً ، الصناديق المشتركة
are to investing,
أوجدت من أجل الإستثمار
but with a twist --
ولكن بطريقة خاصة
because often a community forms around these funds,
لأنه عادة ما تتكون المجتمعات حول هذه الصناديق
as it has at Acumen and other places.
كما حصل في اكيومن أو أماكن أخرى
Now, imagine for a second
الآن تخيلوا للحظة
these first three types of experiments:
أن أنواع التجارب الثلاث
mass collaboration, online marketplaces, aggregated giving.
التعاون الجماعي ، والأسواق الإلكترونية ، والمنح المجمّعة
And understand how they help us re-perceive
و أفهموا كيف يمكنها أن تساعدنا في أن نعيد النظر
what organized philanthropy is.
في ما ينظم العمل الخيري
It's not about foundations necessarily; it's about the rest of us.
أنه ليس ضرورة وجود الجمعيات والمؤسسات ، ولكنه متعلق بنا نحن ..
And imagine the mash-up, if you will, of these things, in the future,
وتخيلو الترابط ، اذا شئتم ، لهذه الأشياء في المستقبل
when these things come together in the experiments of the future --
عندما تأتي هذه الأشياء سوية في تجارب المستقبل
imagine that somebody puts up, say,
تخيلوا أن شخصاً وقف ليقول
100 million dollars
100 مليون دولار
for an inspiring goal --
لهدف ملهم
there were 21 gifts of 100 million dollars or more in the US last year,
كان هناك 21 هدية بـ 100 مليون دولار وأكثر في الولايات المتحدة السنة الماضية
not out of the question --
ليست غير واردة --
but only puts it up if it's matched
ولكنها فقط ترفع عندما تتوافق
by millions of small gifts from around the globe,
بملايين الهدايا الصغيرة من جميع أنحاء العالم
thereby engaging lots of people,
وبذلك يشترك الكثير من الناس
and building visibility and engaging people
وتبنى الجدوى والتواصل مع الناس
in the goal that's stated.
للهدف الذي تم تحديده
I'm going to look quickly at the fourth and fifth categories,
سالقي النظر سريعاً على التصنيف الرابع والخامس
which are innovation, competitions and social investing.
وهما الإبتكار التنافسي ، والإستثمار الإجتماعي
They're betting a visible competition, a prize,
لذلك وضع مسابقة واضحة لجائزة
can attract talent and money to some of the most difficult issues,
قد يجذب العديد من المواهب والأموال لأكثر الأحداث صعوبة
and thereby speed the solution.
وبذلك تسريع إيجاد الحل
This tackles yet another assumption,
وهذا يرمز لإفتراض أخر
that the giver and the organization is at the center,
أن المتبرع والجمعيه هم في المنتصف
as opposed to putting the problem at the center.
بدلاً من وضع المشكلة في المنتصف
You can look to these innovators
يمكنكم النظر لهؤلاء المبتكرين
to help us especially with things that require
ليساعدوننا خصوصاً في الأشياء التي تتطلب
technological or scientific solution.
حلاً تقنياً أو علمياً
That leaves the final category, social investing,
وهذا يترك التصنيف الأخير ، الإستثمار الإجتماعي
which is really, anyway, the biggest of them all,
والذي هو حقيقة ، على أي حال ، أكبرهم كلهم
represented here by Xigi.net.
ممثلاً هنا في شبكة زيقي Xigi.net
And this, of course, tackles the biggest assumption of all,
وهذا بالطبع يرمز لأكبر فرضية فيهم
that business is business,
أن التجارة تجارة
and philanthropy is the vehicle of people who want to create change in the world.
وأن العمل الإنساني هو ناقلة الناس الذين يودون تغيير العالم
Xigi is a new community site
زيقي هي شبكة إجتماعية جديدة
that's built by the community,
بنيت من خلال المجتمع
linking and mapping this new social capital market.
لتربط وتخطط مع راس المال الإجتماعي هذا
It lists already 1,000 entities
في قائمتها أكثر من ألف مؤسسة
that are offering debt and equity for social enterprise.
التي تعرض توفير القروض والأسهم للشركات الإجتماعية
So we can look to these innovators
إذا يمكننا النظر لهؤلاء المبتكرين
to help us remember
ليساعدونا في أن نتذكر
that if we can leverage even a small amount of the capital
أنه كان يمكننا أن نبني حتى على مبلغ رأس مال صغير
that seeks a return,
والتي تهدف للعودة
the good that can be driven could be astonishing.
بالنفع الذي يمكن أن يكون مردوده مذهلاً
Now, what's really interesting here
الآن ، ماهو مثير هنا
is that we're not thinking our way
أننا لانفكر بطريقتنا
into a new way of acting;
في طرق جديدة للحراك
we're acting our way into a new way of thinking.
بل نحن نتجاوب بطريقتنا مع طرق تفكير جديدة
Philanthropy is reorganizing itself
إن العمل الخيري يعيد تنظيم نفسه
before our very eyes.
وأمام أعيننا
And even though all of the experiments and all of the big givers
وعلى الرغم من ذلك فكل التجارب وكل المتبرعين الكبار
don't yet fulfill this aspiration,
لم يستكملوا هذا الالهام
I think this is the new zeitgeist:
أظن أن هذا هو روح العصر
open, big, fast, connected,
منفتح ، ضخم ، سريع ، متصل
and, let us also hope, long.
ولنأمل أيضاً ، بعيداً
We have got to realize that it is going to take a long time to do these things.
بأننا كنا نصدق بأنها ستأخذ وقتا طويلاً لعمل هذه الأشياء
If we don't develop the stamina to stick with things --
مالم نطور لياقتنا ، للمواكبة الأشياء
whatever it is you pick, stick with it --
مهما كانت أنتم أختاروا ، وقفوا معها
all of this stuff is just going to be, you know, a fad.
كل هذه الأشياء ستكون ، كما تعرفون ، موضة
But I'm really hopeful.
ولكنني فعلا أامل خيرا
And I'm hopeful because it's not only philanthropy
ومتفائلة ليس فقط أن العمل الخيري
that's reorganizing itself,
سيعيد ترتيب نفسه
it's also whole other portions of the social sector,
بل كذلك كل القطاعات، المجتمع
and of business,
وفي قطاع الأعمال
that are busy challenging "business as usual."
الذي ينشغلون بتحدي بعضهم كالعاده
And everywhere I go, including here at TED,
وفي كل مكان أذهب إليه بمافيه هنا في تيد
I feel that there is a new moral hunger
أحس أن هناك جوع أخلاقي جديد
that is growing.
أخذ ينمو
What we're seeing is people really wrestling
مانراه فعلا أناس يتصارعون
to describe what is this new thing that's happening.
لتوضيح ماهية الأشياء الجديدة الحاصلة
Words like "philanthrocapitalism,"
كلمات كـ " الرأسمالية الخيرية"
and "natural capitalism," and "philanthroentrepreneur,"
و "الرأسمالية الطبيعية " و "رأسمالية المبادرين"
and "venture philanthropy."
و"الإستثمار المجتمعي"
We don't have a language for it yet.
وليس لدينا لغة لها بعد
Whatever we call it,
مهما سميناها
it's new, it's beginning,
أنها جديدة ، إنها البداية
and I think it's gong to quite significant.
وأظن أنها ستكون واضحة جلياً
And that's where my imagined future comes in,
وهنا يأتي المستقبل المٌتخيل
which I am going to call the social singularity.
والذي سأسميه بالإجتماعية الفردية
Many of you will realize that I'm ripping a bit off of the science fiction writer
كثير منكم قد يرون أني أقتبس قليلاً من كاتب الخيال العلمي
Vernor Vinge's notion of a technological singularity,
فيرنر فينجي ورؤيته للفردية التقنية
where a number of trends accelerate and converge
عندما يتسارع عددا من الموجات وتتقارب
and come together to create, really, a shockingly new reality.
لتأتي سويتاً ، فعلاً ، بحقيقة جديدة صاعقة
It may be that the social singularity
قد يكون أن الأحادية الإجتماعية
ahead is the one that we fear the most:
قدماً هي أكثر شي نخافه
a convergence of catastrophes,
المصائب المتلاحقة
of environmental degradation,
من التدهور البيئي
of weapons of mass destruction, of pandemics,
لأسلحة الدمار الشامل ، ومن الأوبئة
of poverty.
ومن الفقر
That's because
وهذا لأن
our ability to confront the problems that we face
قدراتنا على مجابهة المشاكل التي تواجهنا
has not kept pace with our ability to create them.
لم تماثل قدرتنا على صنعها
And as we've heard here,
وكما سمعنا هنا
it is no exaggeration to say
أنه بلا مبالغة نقول
that we hold the future of our civilization in our hands
أننا نملك مستقبل البشرية في أيدينا
as never before.
كما لم يسبق
The question is, is there a positive social singularity?
والسؤال هو ، هل هناك أحادية إجتماعية إيجابية
Is there a frontier for us
هل هناك حدود بيننا
of how we live together?
لكيفية العيش معاً؟
Our future doesn't have to be imagined.
مستقبلنا لا يجب أن متخيلاً
We can create a future where hope and history rhyme.
نحن يمكننا أن نصنع مستقبلاً مأمولاً ومتناسقاً مع تاريخنا
But we have a problem.
ولكن لدينا مشكلة
Our experience to date, both individually and collectively,
تجاربنا حتى اليوم ، أفراداً وجماعات
hasn't prepared us for what we're going to need to do,
لم تزودنا بما نحتاج أن نفعله
or who we're going to need to be.
أو من نريد أن نكون
We are going to need
نحن سنحتاج
a new generation of citizen leaders
لجيل جديد من القادة الإجتماعين
willing to commit ourselves to growing and changing and learning
الذين يريدون الإلتزام بالنمو والتغيير والتعلم
as rapidly as possible.
بأسرع ما يمكن
That's why I have one last thing I want to show you.
لهذا لدي شئ أخير أود أعرضه لكم
This is a photograph taken about 100 years ago
هذه صورة تم أخذها قبل 100 سنة
of my grandfather and great-grandfather.
لجدي مع جدي الأعظم
This is a newspaper publisher and a banker.
هذا مؤسس جريدة والأخر مصرفي
And they were great community leaders.
وقد كانوا قاده أجتماعيين عظماء
And, yes, they were great philanthropists.
ونعم قد كانوا أهل خير جيدين
I keep this photograph close by to me --
لقد أحتفظت بهذه الصورة قريبا مني
it's in my office --
أنها في مكتبي
because I've always felt a mystical connection to these two men,
لأنني دائما أحسست برابط عجيب مع الرجلين
both of whom I never knew.
وكلاهما لم أعرفه
And so, in their honor,
لذا ، وعلى شرفهم
I want to offer you this blank slide.
أريد أن أعرض عليكم هذه الشريحة الفاضية
And I want you to imagine
وأريدكم أن تتخيلوا
that this a photograph of you.
أن هذه صورة لكم
And I want you to think about the community
وأريدكم أن تفكروا في المجتمع
that you want to be part of creating.
الذي تريدون أن تكون جزءً من صنعه
Whatever that means to you.
غض النظر عن معنى ذلك لك
And I want you to imagine
وأريدكم أن تتخيلوا
that it's 100 years from now,
أنه بعد 100 سنة من الآن
and your grandchild, or great-grandchild,
وأن أحفادكم وأحفادهم
or niece or nephew or god-child,
أو أبناء أخوانكم أو أخواتكم
is looking at this photograph of you.
ينظرون لهذه الصورة لكم
What is the story you most want for them to tell?
ماهي أفضل قصة تريدهم أن يقصوها
Thank you very much.
شكرا جزيلاً لكم
(Applause)
تصفييييييييق